<?xml version='1.0'?>
<!DOCTYPE annotated PUBLIC "annotated.dtd" "annotated.dtd">
<annotated version="1.0">
  <meta>
    <transcriber>ug</transcriber>
    <date>2013-04-22</date>
    <place>Aberdeen</place>
    <author><gender>m</gender><age>42</age><region>Edinburgh</region></author>
    <author><gender>f</gender><age>26</age><region>Shetland</region></author>
  </meta>
  <text>
    <heading>I. Meta data</heading>
    <p>The frame appearing on top of each file contains background 
    information about the raw data.</p>
    <p>Transcriber: the person annotating this raw data file - please 
    use a two-letter code</p>
    <p>Date: date of publication in the format year-month-day (if one 
    or more are unknown put a ? instead (e.g. 2007-06-?)</p>
    <p>Place: place of publication. For online publications please 
    insert the URL.</p>
    <p>Author: give gender as &apos;m&apos; or &apos;f&apos;, age and 
    regional background (where they were born and raused) of author. If 
    not known please put a ?</p>
    <p>If the text has a further author you can create another author 
    line by clicking right behind the last arrow of the element 
    &quot;regional background&quot;. &quot;Author&quot; pops up again. 
    In order to create another element &quot;gender&quot;, 
    &quot;age&quot; etc. press Ctrl+space and select them 
    accordingly.</p>
    <heading>II. Annotation of text properties</heading>
    <heading>1. Headings and paragraphs</heading>
    <p>Before you type in the heading click with the left-mouse button 
    under the last paragraph before your heading until you see a 
    horizontal line. Press Ctrl+space and select heading. Type in the 
    heading and it will appear in bold.</p>
    <p>A paragraph is annotated automatically for every line break. 
    Please make sure that there are no empty lines between paragraphs 
    as they will be falsely annotated as empty paragraphs (you can see 
    this is the &quot;Outline&quot; window on the right).</p>
    <heading>2. Unclear transcription</heading>
    <p>If you cannot read a word in a handwritten text, please do not 
    guess what it might be but mark it as an uncertain transcription by 
    clicking with the right-mouse button at the appropriate place in 
    the transcription and selecting &quot;unclear&quot;. Three ??? will 
    appear.</p>
    <p>Markup: the <unclear words="1"/> car</p>
    <heading>3. Linebreak marker</heading>
    <p>If a line-break appears in an unusual place (e.g.in the middle 
    of a word) mark it by clicking behind the word, pressing Ctrl+space 
    and selecting &quot;break&quot;.</p>
    <p>Example: In spit<break />eful ways</p>
    <heading>4. Punctuation marks</heading>
    <p>Please mark unusual division of words by hyphen (in hand-written 
    texts only): Type in the hyphen, select it, press Ctrl+space and 
    select &quot;punctuation&quot;.</p>
    <p>Example: An unu<punctuation>-</punctuation>sual division</p>
    <p>Please mark all dots that do not function as full stops, e.g. 
    dots in numbers and dates or after abbreviations. Select the dot, 
    press Ctrl+space and select &quot;punctuation&quot;.</p>
    <p>Example: Dr<punctuation>.</punctuation> No</p>
    <heading>5. Text format: Boldface, italic, underline, superscript, 
    subscript, small capitals, change of typeface</heading>
    <p>Mark boldface etc. by selecting the numbers/word, pressing 
    Ctrl+space and selecting the appropriate element.</p>
    <p>Annotated boldface: This <boldface>is</boldface> true.</p>
    <p>Annotated italics: This is <italics>true</italics>.</p>
    <p>Annotated underline: <underline>This</underline> is true.</p>
    <p>Annotated superscript: 22<superscript>nd</superscript></p>
    <p>Annotated subscript: H<subscript>2</subscript>O (unfortunately 
    shown with overline instead as subscript)</p>
    <p>Annotated small capitals: These are <small-capitals>small 
    capitals</small-capitals>.</p>
    <p>Annotated change of typeface: Change of 
    <typeface-change>typeface</typeface-change>.</p>
    <heading>6. Quotations</heading>
    <p>Very brief quotations which the author of the text has 
    incorporated into the structure of his own sentence should be 
    marked as quotes, as in the following example. Select the 
    quotation, press Ctrl+space and select &quot;quote&quot;.</p>
    <p>Example: The starting point for such a method was to be 
    &quot;simple sensuous perception&quot;, from which the mind would 
    be led step-by-step, &quot;as if by machinery&quot;, to inductive 
    proof.</p>
    <p>Markup: The starting point for such a method was to be 
    <quote>&quot;simple sensuous perception&quot;</quote>, from which 
    the mind would be led step-by-step, <quote>&quot;as if by 
    machinery&quot;</quote>, to inductive proof.</p>
    <heading>7. Colloquialism</heading>
    <p>Mark colloquialism in the text by selecting the word, pressing 
    Ctrl+space and selecting &quot;coll&quot;. In the Properties window 
    (usually hiding behind the Console window in the bottom right-hand 
    corner. You can also make it visible by clicking on 
    Window-Show-View-Other-Properties) type in the standard notation 
    (property &quot;for&quot;):</p>
    <p>Example: This is 4u!</p>
    <p>Markup: This is <coll for="for you">4u</coll>!</p>
    <heading>8. Deleted words</heading>
    <p>Mark words that were deleted by the author (usually in 
    hand-written texts). Select the word by double-clicking on it, 
    press Ctrl+space and select &quot;deleted&quot;. The word will 
    appear as shown below:</p>
    <p>Example: the fantastic wonderful show</p>
    <p>Markup: the <deleted>fantastic</deleted> wonderful show</p>
    <heading>9. Discontinuous words</heading>
    <p>Discontinuous words typically occur in cases of tmesis, when one 
    word is inserted within another. Very rare in written texts! Select 
    the word by double-clicking on it, press Ctrl+space and select 
    &quot;discontinous&quot;. The word will appear as shown below:</p>
    <p>Example: the fan-bloody-tastic show</p>
    <p>Markup: the <discontinuous corrected="bloody fantastic">
    fan-bloody tastic</discontinuous> show</p>
    <heading>10. Signature, footnote</heading>
    <p>Instead of typing in the signature, press Ctrl+space and select 
    &quot;signature&quot;. Mark footnotes by pressing Ctrl+space and 
    selecting &quot;footnote&quot;.</p>
    <p>Example: John Smith</p>
    <p>Markup: <signature>John Smith</signature></p>
    <p>Markup footnote: <footnote>This is a footnote</footnote>.</p>
    <heading>11. Untranscribable elements</heading>
    <p>Mark up formulas, graphs etc in the raw data by clicking at the 
    appropriate position, pressing Ctrl+space and selecting 
    &quot;object&quot;. In the Properties window (usually hiding behind 
    the Console window in the bottom right-hand corner. You can also 
    make it visible by clicking on Window-Show-View-Other-Properties) 
    please select whether it is a table, formula, picture etc.</p>
    <p>Example: text text picture text</p>
    <p>Markup: text text <object type="graphic"/> text</p>
    <heading>12. Corrections of the text: Misspellings, superfluous 
    words</heading>
    <p>In general, please make as few corrections as possible. Do not 
    correct grammatical errors, or what may be perceived as grammatical 
    or stylistic deviations. This is what we are interested in!</p>
    <p>12 a) Misspellings: Select the word by double-clicking on it. 
    Press Ctrl+space and select error. In the Properties window 
    (usually hiding behind the Console window in the bottom right-hand 
    corner. You can also make it visible by clicking on 
    Window-Show-View-Other-Properties) type in the correct spelling 
    under &quot;value&quot;. The word marked as an error will appear as 
    shown below:</p>
    <p>Example: But that&apos;s rank hypocrasy!</p>
    <p>Markup: But that&apos;s rank <error corrected="hypocrisy">
    hypocrasy</error>!</p>
    <p>If a word is spelled incorrectly, but the intended correct word 
    is not conceivable from the spelling, in the Properties window type 
    in &quot;?&quot;.</p>
    <p>Example: They crashed into <error corrected="?">
    parces</error>.</p>
    <p>Corrected version: ?</p>
    <p>If alternative accepted spellings exist for a word, in the 
    Properties window type in both accepted spellings in alphabetical 
    order separated by a comma:</p>
    <p>Example: The house <error corrected="burned,burnt">
    burnd</error>.</p>
    <p>Corrected version: burned,burnt</p>
    <p>12 b) Clearly superfluous words can be deleted in the following 
    way: Select the word by double-clicking on it. Press Ctrl+space and 
    select error. In the Properties window (usually hiding behind the 
    Console window in the bottom right-hand corner. You can also make 
    it visible by clicking on Window-Show-View-Other-Properties) select 
    &quot;yes&quot; next to &quot;superfluous&quot;. The word marked as 
    superfluous will appear as shown below:</p>
    <p>Example: I didn&apos;t know know that!</p>
    <p>Markup: I didn&apos;t know <error superfluous="true">
    know</error> that!</p>
    <heading>13. Mentions</heading>
    <p>Mark words which are cited as words. Select the word by 
    double-clicking on it, press Ctrl+space and select 
    &quot;mention&quot;. The word will appear as shown below.</p>
    <p>Example: Dog is a noun.</p>
    <p>Markup: <mention>Dog</mention> is a noun.</p>
    <heading>III. Other annotations</heading>
    <heading>1. Editorial comments</heading>
    <p>This is used to mark essential comments made by the person 
    applying the markup. Use it sparingly, and only when no other 
    markup symbol is applicable.An editorial comment can be used, for 
    example, to explain an unusual abbreviation. You can also use it as 
    a note to yourself - please put in your ID-code then.</p>
    <p>Example: He went out and bought a vid.</p>
    <p>Markup: He went out and bought a vid 
    <editor-comment>vid=video</editor-comment>.</p>
    <heading>2. Other language</heading>
    <p>Any longer part of a text or recording that does not consist of 
    English should be marked as &quot;other language&quot;. You can 
    specify with the attribute &apos;language&apos; in the properties 
    window which language the passage is in.</p>
    <p>Example: My wife has no access to email. Dè an t-ainm a tha 
    oirbh?</p>
    <p>Markup:My wife has no access to email. <other-language>Dè an 
    t-ainm a tha oirbh?</other-language></p>
    <heading>2. Anonymisation of names, places, email 
    addresses</heading>
    <p>Delete proper names in private (i.e. unpublished documents and 
    recordings) in order to preserve anonymity. Press Ctrl+space and 
    select &quot;x-anonym-x&quot;. In the Properties window (usually 
    hiding behind the Console window in the bottom right-hand corner. 
    If not to be found, you can make it visible by clicking on 
    Window-Show-View-Other-Properties.) choose whether you are 
    anonymizing a first name, last name, location, email address 
    etc.</p>
    <p>Example: Dr Brown of London University</p>
    <p>Markup: Dr <x-anonym-x type="family-name"/> of 
    <x-anonym-x type="location"/> University</p>
    <heading>IV. Steps in carrying out an annotation</heading>
    <p>The green line at the bottom of the annotation file specifies 
    the steps that need to be carried out. Remove this TODO marker by 
    clicking between the brackets and pressing del. After transcription 
    and annotation please check the spelling by copying the text into 
    Word. Then, run the Build script and check whether everything 
    appears ok in the index.html created in the ship folder. Lastly, 
    check in your new transcription by committing your work. Well 
    done!</p>
    <heading>V. Extra-corpus material</heading>
    <p>Passages that are not annotated at all (because one file is 
    longer than 2,000 words for example) are marked as 
    &quot;unannotated&quot; by pressing Ctrl+space and selecting 
    &quot;unannotated&quot;.</p>
    <p>Example: This sentence is the last one to be annotated.</p>
    <unannotated>All the rest of the text is extra-corpus, in ICE 
    parlance.</unannotated>
  </text>
  <TODO-1 />
  <TODO-2 />
</annotated>
